Hello and welcome to Organic
Chemistry with ItsDrdan.
And this is our first episode of
how we are going to be explaining
introductory, organic and biochemistry,
mainly aimed towards pre- allied
health majors and the health sciences.
So with this particular playlist, as
I begin to make it, It's going to go
through fundamental skills to be able
to help you with the introduction and
basics behind organic and biochemistry.
So only the fundamentals.
It's not about trying to go through
arrow notation and every little detail,
it's just how to go through basics.
So where does it all start?
So with this, it's all about
the chemistry of carbon.
So carbon is the center of our world, no
matter if it's organic or in biochemistry.
It's all about carbon.
And what really, if you can kind of
remember from your basics, from general
chemistry, what made carbon so important
was its ability to be able to make bonds.
And if you can remember, carbon in
particular has four valence electrons
around it, meaning that it can make
four bonds around on all sides, and
that's what we're gonna be focusing
on today as we go through this.
So let's first take a look on if
we can make four bonds of carbon.
What other important bonding
trends do we need to know before
going into organic chemistry?
Okay, so with bonding trends
that we are gonna commonly see.
So most of these are based off
your periodic table where there are
trends that show how many bonds.
So with organic chemicals, most of 'em
are dealing with carbon and hydrogen,
particularly hydrocarbons, which
we'll talk about later in this video.
So carbon, as I said earlier, it
can make a total of four bonds.
Now what else is there?
Well, hydrogen was
another common component.
Well, hydrogen can make up to
one bond, and that was due to
its one valence electron it had.
So hydrogen could do
one and carbon could do.
Four that we're all around it now.
How does that trend continue?
Well, if you kind of can think
about it, well, nitrogen is right
next to it, and that can do a
total of three bonds around it.
Oxygen can do two.
All of the halogen on the far right
hand side of the periodic table can
all do one based on the number of
bonds that they all have around them.
So if you can remember those little
trends, that is what we're going
to be using to help us go forward
with all these different parts of
the class, um, depending on how
many bonds you exactly are making.
And here we have all the
individual Lewis structures.
For each of those
individual species as well.
So let's go on to what other things we
have to know about organic chemistry.
So when it comes to organic, the
other thing is, is how are you going
to be seeing molecules in organic?
I.
There are four different ways
that you're gonna see this.
The first way is chemical and
molecular formulas, which is from
the same thing as general chemistry.
So molecular formulas are all referring
to, let's say, if I had a, either
a two carbon species, like, uh,
ethane, which we'll talk about the
naming and future videos, so C2H6.
Or let's say with methane CH4 or C3H8
for propane, we can show all those
individual structures via their formula.
However, this does not tell us any
of the particular bonding patterns
that we see within these molecules.
It just tell you how many
carbons, how many hydrogens.
But a big component of this is how
does it bond in organic chemistry?
That is what we wanna know.
So there's three ways to show
how something is bonding.
The first one is complete
structural formulas.
It's also sometimes called line bond.
Or, um, full structures as well.
So if we're to use, let's say, if we
use the example that I have on the
right hand side here with propane,
uh, throughout this, so how would we
show that complete structural formula?
Well, we would show our
carbons all bonding together.
Being that this is the
chemistry of carbon.
We're gonna constantly be showing
chains of carbon connecting together.
We'll then have our
hydrogens fill in the rest.
So remember, we have a total of
four bonds on every single carbon,
and we can show that as well.
So we will fill all those in.
And just to look at, let's say if I look
at the first carbon here, we can quickly
count all the bonds around it, right?
We see 1, 2, 3.
Four bonds all around that carbon,
and we can do that for every single
one of those structures that we draw.
We are always counting to the magic
number four as we're going through them.
So now with condensed structure, the
way to think about this one is if
you are, if you are playing a game
on your phone and you have to collect
different pieces, To almost, um, in a
sense to collect tokens or, or bounties
or all kinds of things like that.
Well, this is the same way.
Essentially, if I take and I click
each one of my carbons here and I want
to minimize them to help make this
condensed, we can show that as well.
So if I have my first carbon right,
so the CH3 on the end, so that was.
This carbon here, we can
minimize that all down.
Now, if I go to the second carbon,
we can do the same thing as well
where we show CH2, and then I can
do it again on the third carbon to
show, okay, we have CH3-CH2-CH3.
Now notice if I number
those one, two, and three.
It's showing that bonding
pattern and it's minimizing all
those individual structures.
Skeletal formula is the last way,
which is the easiest out of all of 'em.
It's the same thing as saying geometric
because alls we're gonna be drawing
is lines to show the different bonds.
So what do I mean by that?
Well, if I want to do propane,
which is three carbons, this is
all I would show is just like this.
Now what exactly is that showcasing?
Well, each of these little,
uh, vertices or corners.
Represents a carbon.
Okay?
And it's assumed that they have all
four bonds around it, meaning that
this has its prospective number
of hydrogens with it as well.
So if I wanted to expand that a
little bit more, I could show that.
All right, well, I have CH3-CH2-CH3.
Or we can even try to expand that
a little bit more because not only
is it showing the geometries behind
this, but we can also see the total
of number of hydrogens as well.
So the correct one is the one all the
way up in that top left hand side, but we
can, this is the idea behind geometric.
It simplifies it, but it still
shows all of our numbers of
hydrogens that we have here as well.
So let me move that over.
See that behind me.
We can easily showcase
all those little pieces.
Let's do an example together.
If I say, let's do an example.
Let's say we wanna find all those little
pieces for C4H10, also known as butane.
So with this one, first thing
is, well, how do we find 'em?
Molecular formula?
Well, we already were given it, right?
So C4H10 would be our
answer for that first part.
Now the complete structural formula is,
the whole idea is, is showing this in like
a 90 degree, completely expanded out form.
So complete structural line
bond, expanded formula.
These are all referring to the same thing.
First thing we start with is writing our
four carbons in a chain all altogether.
And now what we're gonna do
is we're gonna fill in all of
our hydrogens along with that.
So we'll do that in this different color.
And we have one, two.
Three hydrogens all on the first carbon.
Notice how there's a
total of four bonds there.
So I'll even highlight a little bond
here in yellow just to show that.
And then for our next one, I'll do
that in different colors as well
to help illustrate all the bonds.
So notice how's 1, 2, 3, 4.
Then we'll go to the next one, right?
1, 2, 3, and four.
And then we'll finish our
last one by filling in.
All of the hydrogens in another color.
So we have four bonds on each
individual carbon for that
complete structural formula.
Now, the next part is, like I
mentioned, it's like clicking
each of these little carbons.
So clicking carbons, carbon 1, 2,
3, and four, and minimizing them.
So how would we do that?
Well, the first one, right, we'd
have CH3, and then we'd have CH2.
And then we would have CH2, and then CH3.
So trying to color code that
so they stick together, right?
You see that minimization
that's occurring.
The skeletal formula is just
doing our little zigzag pattern.
And the whole reason we're showing those
zigzags is because it shows geometries,
which will cover in future videos as well.
So talking about tetrahedral
geometries for this particular one.
So being that we will have this, it'll
be 1, 2, 3, 4, and just to kind of tell
you, right, this represents that CH3,
then CH2, CH2, and then CH3 behind that
particular structure with the zigzag
pattern, and we can even put that in the
individual lines to help illustrate that.
As we are going to do that in this
type of, in this course or this
understanding of organic chemicals.
Let's go on to the next topic.
In organic chemistry, what we're gonna
find out is that all these molecules
are hydrocarbons, meaning that they're
mainly made up of carbon and hydrogen.
These are evolving around three
major types of hydrocarbons.
The first one is referring to all
Alkanes, alkanes are telling you that
they're all single bonded carbons.
Alkenes are double bonded carbons.
And then alkynes have a triple
bond in between those carbons.
And what we're gonna be looking for
as we are writing these hydrocarbons
is if it has a one of these different
types of species with inside of their
chains, which we are gonna, as we draw
them, if you have one of them that
tells you the type, now one thing that
you can maybe take a notice of is what
is really different between all these.
And that is the ending here, right?
So we have -ane, -ene, -yne
for alkene, alkene, and alkyne.
Well, what these have to do tell you
about is that, well, when we are looking
at all these different chains, also known
as as cyclic chains as well, so there's
just continuous chain or not a branch.
When we have them, they have
different endings behind them.
So all these individual endings,
and here we're gonna move this.
So with all the endings, they
ha they tell you, uh, exactly
what is important about them.
So their ending are suffix in the name,
which is gonna be important in part two
of this, it tells you their functional
group or their organic family, which gives
you an idea of really what properties
are they capable of as we are going
through all these little individual types.
So it's something that is extremely
important for our understanding
of how they are going to behave.
As a chemical compound.
So let's look at this a little bit
further in different other, some
other different pieces of information
that you're gonna commonly hear in
organic chemistry is referring to
something known as the longest carbon
chain or the parent carbon chain.
So what this referring to is
whenever we are looking at an organic
hydrocarbon or structure, We are
always looking for the longest chain.
So for example, going through through
these, there's a long list of them.
Here's the first six of them.
Generally we go up to the first 10
for us to be able to look at them.
We're gonna, let's draw
the geometric structures.
So the first one is methane,
which we don't bother drawing
the geometric, we just write CH4,
but we can even go past that.
The next one, ethane is two carbons.
So ethane is referring to whether
it's, you write it as the CH3, CH3,
or it can also be written as a line
illustrating that structure with propane.
That was the example
that we first did, right?
That looks like a little, almost
like a little arrow, and that's
shown that CH3, CH2,  CH3.
Butane, right?
We're gonna still take that
same shape, but we're gonna
add one more carbon onto it.
And the same thing with
pentane going down, right?
We're just increasing
the length of the chain.
And the same thing with hexane.
We are just increasing that length
by one carbon each time, and we can
show that each one of those little,
little corners are one more carbon
as you're going through them, right?
We're gonna consistently count.
All of our carbons as we are
looking at the parent chain.
So as you're going through these
examples, you're trying to figure
out, okay, what is your longest
chain as you're going through these?
And that is one of our key takeaways.
What else will we see other than parent
change is gonna be something known as sub.
Let's go onto the next thing.
The last key word that we're gonna show
in this video is different branches or
substituents, which is a common thing
you're gonna see connected to all of these
different parent chains or longest chains.
So there are a bunch
of common substituents.
Here I have four of 'em listed, which
are methyl, ethyl, propyl, and butyl.
And these are cheal chain chains.
So notice that it has
that -yl ending here.
What this is referring to is that, okay,
this is a branch, so it's something
that's a, almost like an extra piece
or appendage to our longest chain.
Let's take a look at this.
So let's say if I draw a
pentane here, let's show some
example of different chains.
So if I go off this first part here
where I have just a methyl attached
to this, so this is a CH3, this
is an example of a methyl chain.
There are, we could continuously
add to this as well.
So let's say if I wanted to make
this a little bit longer and do
the next one, which is Ethel.
Well, alls we would have to do is show
that chain increasing in size just like
this, and what this here is showing that,
all right, well we have a CH2 and CH3
substituent, which is known as ethyl.
Now, that can continuously
grow even farther, possibly.
So let's say if we had
a longer chain here.
And I decided to add a three carbon
chain to the end, which is 1, 2, 3.
This would be an example of a propyl.
Okay.
So that would be propal, right?
So three coming off.
And then if, as you can kind of imagine
with that trend there, if we have a four
carbon one coming off, or our branch
coming off, and that's going to be butyl.
So one, two.
Three, four all coming off of that chain.
Right?
So then that would show the last
one, which is a butyl group.
Now, typically they don't
usually get longer than butyl.
Butyl is typically the maximum
being that it's all about what
is your longest parent chain.
And as we're going through, this
is a basic introduction of our
different verbiage that we're gonna
be going through this video series.
Um, we're gonna go into our next video,
which is gonna be all about functional
groups and how we can see how this
is going to define not only what your
chain's name is, but also the properties
behind it as well as we go through all
these different theories of videos.
Alright.
Thank you for stopping by and I
hope you should check out part two.
And this has been Dr.
Dan, please hit that like and
subscribe button, and I hope to see
you again next time in the future.
Bye now.